<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A letter from a gentleman to his friend, on the treaty for dividing the Spanish monarchy, if the king of Spain should die without a son</title>
            <author>W. K.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1700</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 7 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 2 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A47213</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing K25</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R213549</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99825903</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99825903</idno>
            <idno type="VID">30294</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A47213)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 30294)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1795:37)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A letter from a gentleman to his friend, on the treaty for dividing the Spanish monarchy, if the king of Spain should die without a son</title>
                  <author>W. K.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>1 sheet ([2] p.)   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed for J. Nutt near Stationers-Hall,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1700.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signed at end: W.K.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Harvard University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Charles --  II, --  King of Spain, 1661-1700 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:30294:1"/>
            <head>A LETTER From a Gentleman to his Friend, ON THE TREATY For DIVIDING the Spaniſh Monarchy, IF THE KING of SPAIN Should DIE without a SON.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I wonder that the Treaty and Deſign of Divinding the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Monarchy ſhould make a Noiſe, and raiſe ſuch violent Diſcourſes as I have heard, and ſuch Threatnings of the Miniſters that adviſed the King to make ſuch a Treaty; as if by that Treaty <hi>France</hi> was already Crown'd Univerſal Monarch of <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rope:</hi> But I ſay, this was certainly the Wiſeſt and moſt Politick thing His Majeſty could do for <hi>England,</hi> next having Redeem'd us from Popery &amp; Slavery.</p>
            <p>And if the King was thereunto adviſed by any of his Council, thoſe Counſellors deſerve to have their Statues ſet up, and have the Publick Thanks and Prayers of the Nation; and our falſe Politicians, who exclaim againſt the ſaid Treaty, will be found either Fools or Knaves, or Malicious Villains, that would diſturb the Government; Some diſcontented Men that have either been turn'd out of their Places for <hi>Jacobi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm,</hi> or that hope to have their Mouths ſtopt with Places or Money; and I expect to ſee them in Print, Spitting their Venom, and ſhewing their Malice, to this our Happy Government.</p>
            <p>But all Wiſe, Honeſt, and true Lovers of <hi>England,</hi> will ſagaciouſly think and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider well, before they exclaim againſt the Actions and Counſels of a King, to whoſe Courage and Wiſdom We, and all <hi>Europe,</hi> owe our Liberty, and the Peace we now Enjoy.</p>
            <p>I pretend neither to Wit nor Eloquence, much leſs to be a Politician, or to be a Privy-Councellor, but I am an <hi>Engliſh</hi>-Man, and hate the Ingratitude of many of my Country-men to this Great Prince whom Heaven has given us.</p>
            <p>Every <hi>Cobler</hi> in <hi>England</hi> is a Politician, Reads the <hi>Gazette</hi> and <hi>Poſt-boy,</hi> then Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches and explains ſome Text from <hi>Ditto,</hi> which the Rabble take for Goſpel, truly ſuch are the Railers at this Treaty, but know nothing of the main Deſign.</p>
            <p>Now Sir, I will not Condemn them without giving my Reaſons for it, as theſe ill People do, without knowing why this Treaty was made; for I dare ſay, they were not ask'd to give their Opinions no more than my ſelf, who do not think it Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary to write a Volume of what is ſaid on this Subject, nor is it fit for me to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to Penetrate into a Kings Thoughts, but I plainly give you mine, and Thoughts ought to be free.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:30294:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p> 
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> I do believe the Diſtemper of the King of <hi>Spain</hi> may be the Cauſe that the <hi>French</hi> King was ſo deſirous for a Peace, that he might be at Liberty to aſſert the <hi>Dauphius</hi> Pretenſions to the Crown of <hi>Spain,</hi> if the King of <hi>Spain</hi> Dyed; and for ought I know, <hi>France</hi> may have made an offer to the King, or his Miniſters at the Treaty at <hi>Reyſwick;</hi> if <hi>France</hi> did make that offer, pray tell me was it not Wiſely and Poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tickly done, if his Majeſty or his Miniſters ſhould anſwer, that it would not be proper at that time and place, leſt the <hi>Emperour</hi> and <hi>Spain</hi> ſhould break off the Treaty.</p>
            <p>If the <hi>French</hi> did obtain a Promiſe for this Treaty, when the Peace was made, and all the Towns and Countreys delivered up, I ſay if they did; Pray tell me, was it not reaſonable and fit <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Holland</hi> ſhould make good their Promiſe, by which the ſo much deſired Peace was obtained, and a Petty Kingdom given back, which <hi>France</hi> cannot retake in Twenty years, tho' <hi>England</hi> ſtood Neuter; Theſe Towns have enlarged and Strengthned the Barrier of <hi>Holland</hi> and <hi>Flanders,</hi> which is the Intereſt of <hi>England</hi> to the higheſt Degree; for were <hi>Holland</hi> and <hi>Flanders</hi> o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver-run, pray what would become of <hi>England?</hi> This was thought of in King <hi>Charles</hi> his Reign, who put a ſtop to the <hi>French</hi> Conqueſts, when <hi>France</hi> was at the very Gates of <hi>Amſterdam.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Next, I conſider this Agreement or Treaty is of no conſequence to the <hi>French</hi> King: For the King of <hi>Spain</hi> is not Dead, he may have a Son; and the <hi>French</hi> King is not Immmortal. But ſuppoſe the King of <hi>Spain</hi> were Dead, and hath no Son; I believe the <hi>Spaniards</hi> will chuſe themſelves a King; the Emperour hath Peace with the <hi>Turk,</hi> and will not eaſily give up his Intereſt, or Abandon the Houſe of <hi>Auſtria; Italy</hi> will hardly chuſe the <hi>French</hi> King for Pope: For <hi>Rome</hi> would ſoon be his, if <hi>Naples, Sicily,</hi> and <hi>Spain</hi> were in his Power; <hi>Venice</hi> will not like ſuch a Neighbour; nor will <hi>Savoy,</hi> or the <hi>Suiſs</hi> be eaſy.</p>
            <p>If now a <hi>French</hi> Man ſhould ask me, What will the <hi>Engliſh</hi> and <hi>Dutch</hi> do, in caſe all theſe Nations oppoſe this Diviſion of the Spaniſh Monarchy? I would anſwer the <hi>French</hi> man with this Queſtion, Whether he would have me take it ill of him, if he did not punctually meet me at the <hi>Royal-Exchange</hi> at 12 a Clock, if he had broke his Leg at <hi>Temple-Bar</hi> at 11.</p>
            <p>Can <hi>France</hi> expect the King of <hi>England</hi> ſhould go a Voluntier in his Army, to force the Emperour, <hi>Spain, Italy, Venice, Savoy,</hi> and the <hi>Suiſs,</hi> to make him Monarch of <hi>Europe?</hi> Or can it be imagin'd (conſidering the value and Jealouſy the Engliſh and Dutch have for their Trade and Liberty) that they will run Headlong to raiſe a Power to devour themſelves,</p>
            <p>Why then all this Noiſe, but Maliciouſly to endeavour to make a Diſcord, between our Great King, and his Good Subjects? Is it not better to think as I do, for I only write my Thoughts, I am no Privy-Counſellor; but I believe it is more Honeſt, and more my Duty, to think the beſt of my Superiors, than Ungratefully to Exclaim againſt them who are ſet over us, and from whence we reap ſuch great Bleſſings as Peace affords, after our Preſervation from Popery and Slavery.</p>
            <p>Thus Sir, I have given you my Reaſons for what I have ſaid on the Subject for Dividing the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Monarchy, in Caſe the King of <hi>Spain</hi> ſhould Dye, and leave no Heir; I am very ſhort on every Paragraph, and not fond of Scribling: And <hi>Hudibras</hi> tells us,
<q>
                  <l>Brevity is always good,</l>
                  <l>Whether we are or are not underſtood.</l>
               </q> Beſides I would not be bid to meddle with my own Buſineſs.</p>
            <closer>This from, <salute>Sir,</salute> 
               <signed>Your Humble Servant <hi>W.K.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>J. Nutt</hi> near <hi>Stationers-Hall,</hi> 1700.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
